<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<dialog xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
        xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="help.xsd"

        id="guess-format" title="Text Import Format" >
    <help id="tableName" title="Table Name">
        <short>The name of the new table.</short>
        <full><p>The name cannot be blank and must be different from all other tables in the project.</p></full>
    </help>
    <help id="linkCopy" title="Link/Copy">
        <short>Whether to copy the data in to the project, or leave it in the file.</short>
        <full><p>There are two options available to import data.  One is to take a copy
            of the data from the file into the project.  Afterwards, the source file
            is forgotten: it can be deleted, moved or edited with no effect on the project.
            This is the best option if you want to access the project from multiple machines.</p>
            <p>The alternative is to link the file.  The source file must be kept afterwards,
                and any changes will be automatically detected by the project.  This is the best
                option for very large datasets, or if you know the file will have its data changed
                in future.</p></full>
    </help>
    <help id="charset" title="Encoding">
        <short>The scheme used to encode characters in the file.  UTF-8 is the most likely choice.</short>
        <full><p>There are lots of different characters in the world: Latin characters (as used in the English alphabet),
            Arabic, Chinese and many more besides.  An encoding scheme is the way in which these characters
        are numbered and stored in a file.  Unfortunately, historically every sub-region had its own encoding,
        and if you get the encoding mismatched, you will get weird characters.  Recently, UTF-8 has become
        something of a common standard, but many other encoding schemes are still in use.  Try UTF-8 first,
            but try then others if that doesn't work.</p></full>
    </help>
    <help id="headerRow" title="Header Rows">
        <short>How many rows to skip at the beginning of the file.</short>
        <full><p>There are often header rows at the beginning of the file which
        do not contain useful data.  This number is how many rows to skip.  The
        last row is taken to be the names of the columns.</p></full>
    </help>
    <help id="quote" title="Quote Character">
        <short>The character used to surround columns.</short>
        <full><p>Text files use a particular character, such as a comma,
        to separate the columns.  But some pieces of text may actually
        contain a comma.  So quotes are sometimes used to surround
        text values in columns.</p></full>
    </help>
    <help id="columnCount" title="Column Count">
        <short>The number of columns to use in the file.</short>
        <full><p>If every row has the same number of columns then
        this is fixed.  If there is a varying number of columns
            then you must specify the current number.</p></full>
    </help>
    <help id="separator" title="Column Separator">
        <short>The character used to separate columns in the file.</short>
        <full><p>The columns in each row need to be separated by a particular
            character, such as a comma or semi-colon.</p></full>
    </help>

</dialog>